<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<knora xmlns="https://dasch.swiss/schema" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://dasch.swiss/schema https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dasch-swiss/dsp-tools/main/src/dsp_tools/resources/schema/data.xsd" shortcode="0011" default-ontology="daschland">
    <permissions id="res-default">
        <allow group="UnknownUser">V</allow>
        <allow group="KnownUser">V</allow>
        <allow group="ProjectMember">D</allow>
        <allow group="ProjectAdmin">CR</allow>
        <allow group="Creator">CR</allow>
    </permissions>
    <permissions id="res-restricted">
        <allow group="UnknownUser">V</allow>
        <allow group="KnownUser">V</allow>
        <allow group="ProjectMember">D</allow>
        <allow group="ProjectAdmin">CR</allow>
        <allow group="Creator">CR</allow>
    </permissions>
    <permissions id="prop-default">
        <allow group="UnknownUser">V</allow>
        <allow group="KnownUser">V</allow>
        <allow group="ProjectMember">D</allow>
        <allow group="ProjectAdmin">CR</allow>
        <allow group="Creator">CR</allow>
    </permissions>
    <permissions id="prop-restricted">
        <allow group="ProjectMember">M</allow>
        <allow group="ProjectAdmin">CR</allow>
        <allow group="Creator">CR</allow>
    </permissions>
    <permissions id="bitstream-prop-restricted">
        <allow group="ProjectMember">M</allow>
        <allow group="ProjectAdmin">CR</allow>
        <allow group="Creator">CR</allow>
        <allow group="UnknownUser">RV</allow>
        <allow group="KnownUser">RV</allow>
    </permissions>
    <resource label="Alice in DaSCHland" restype=":Fairytale" id="F_01" permissions="res-default">
        <text-prop name=":hasID">
            <text permissions="prop-default" encoding="utf8">F_01</text>
        </text-prop>
        <text-prop name=":hasName">
            <text permissions="prop-default" encoding="utf8">Alice in DaSCHland</text>
        </text-prop>
        <text-prop name=":hasDescription">
            <text permissions="prop-default" encoding="xml">In the fairytale "Alice in DaSCHland," a curious young girl named Alice discovers a magical realm powered by DaSCH, a company that operates as a repository for research data in the humanities. This world is filled with technological wonders like talking robots, digital trees, and houses that change color. Guided by a robot named RabbIT, Alice explores various marvels, including a café with size-altering tea and a library with books that speak. She meets the Queen of Hearts, an engineer who creates devices connecting emotions with digital data. Although Alice returns to her world with a token from DaSCHland, the experience leaves her inspired, reminding her that the realm of innovation and dreams, where research data in the humanities are brought to life, awaits her return.</text>
        </text-prop>
    </resource>
    <resource label="Alice in DaSCHland" restype=":Fairytale" id="F_02" permissions="res-default">
        <text-prop name=":hasID">
            <text permissions="prop-default" encoding="utf8">F_02</text>
        </text-prop>
        <text-prop name=":hasName">
            <text permissions="prop-default" encoding="utf8">Alice in DaSCHland</text>
        </text-prop>
        <text-prop name=":hasDescription">
            <text permissions="prop-default" encoding="xml">In the enchanting tale of "Alice in DaSCHland," a young, adventurous girl named Alice finds herself in a fantastical world powered by DaSCH, a pioneering company known for its repository of humanities research data. DaSCHland is a place where technology and imagination merge, featuring sentient robots, trees with digital leaves, and dynamically transforming houses. With the guidance of RabbIT, a robot companion, Alice explores incredible sights, such as a café that offers teas causing her to shrink or grow and a library where books narrate their own stories. She encounters the Queen of Hearts, a brilliant engineer who designs devices that weave human emotions into digital formats. When Alice returns to her own reality, carrying a small, glowing keepsake from her journey, she is left with a sense of wonder and a knowledge that DaSCHland's visionary world, where the humanities data comes alive, will always be there, inviting her to explore further.</text>
        </text-prop>
    </resource>
</knora>
